Finding Aid for the Charles Edgar Little Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Charles Edgar Little Papers
circa 1885-1945
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0260
.84 linear_feet
Biographical Note
Early Life
Charles Edgar Little was born near Eatonton, Georgia November 25, 1865. His father was an estate owner. He was born into a largely Presbyterian family, but attended a nearby Methodist church with his immediate family.
As a boy Little did well at the nearby Enterprise School, worked on the plantation, and enjoyed hunting opossum and raccoons at night. At sixteen he moved to Eatonton to attend Eatonton Academy. To help pay for school he worked as a clerk and bookkeeper at the general store of E.B. Ezell and Company. After mastering the subjects taught at Eatonton, he studied under lawyer Alonzo Reid, a Latin graduate of the University of Georgia. Reid encouraged Little to enroll at Peabody Normal School and is largely responsible for his attendance.
Student Life and Marriage
In summer of 1885, at 19, Little began to teach at Eatonton. He left in the fall to begin at Peabody. Though he was much younger than other students on campus he already had teaching experiences that his comrades lacked. After two years of study he received a Licentiate of Instruction diploma on May 25, 1887.
Once he received his L.I. degree he returned to work at Eatonton Academy. At the age of 22, Little was in charge of the summer session. Just a few months after returning to Eatonton he accepted a position as the principal for an academy in Sparta, Georgia. Two years later he moved back to Eatonton as the assistant principal after the school had reorganized. He taught elementary algebra, Latin grammar, higher algebra, geology, Xenophon, Greek, Latin, bookkeeping, trigonometry, higher arithmetic, English grammar, Horace, Sallust, and French. Little became the principal of the school in 1890.
Wanting to continue his education, Little re-enrolled at Peabody for his baccalaureate degree in 1890-1891. At Peabody he excelled in his studies graduating valedictorian of his class. While at Peabody he met his soon-to-be wife Bessie Chew Jacobs. The two grew close as a result of their similar Presbyterian clergy family history and Peabody experiences. They were married on September 18, 1894.
In 1893 he enrolled in the Doctor of Philosophy program at Vanderbilt University where he chose to major in Latin with Greek and Sanskrit minors. He received his degree in 1899.
Academic Career
Little was appointed as an instructor at Peabody the year of his graduation where he taught Latin and mathematics.
He made an effort to unite alumni of the University of Nashville and convinced Judge Jacob McGavock Dickinson to help found the Alumni Association of University of Nashville and Peabody Normal. Little became the president of the Alumni Association in 1894.
Charles Little became the first editor of The Peabody Record, the journal of the Alumni Association. In 1899 he began to serve as the head of the Latin department as well as the secretary of the faculty, a position he kept until 1911.
In 1911 Peabody Normal College was closed re-opening as the George Peabody College for Teachers reopened at its new campus at Edgehill and Hillsboro three years later with a new faculty, board of trustees, and administration. Little was the only faculty member retained in the move. During this time of disruption, Little catalogued the library and transferred it to the new campus. He published George Peabody College for Teachers, Its Evolution and Present Status in the first bulletin of the new college in 1912. Peabody College for Teachers resumed training teachers in 1914.
He served on the Board of Trustees as assistant secretary in 1911 and secretary and assistant treasurer in January 1914. He served as the secretary until his retirement and as treasurer from 1917 until 1927.
Upon the unexpected death of Bruce Payne on April 21, 1937, Little served as acting president until May 6. He presided over the inauguration of the new president on February 4, 1938.
In 1941 he retired with the title Professor Emeritus of Latin and Secretary of the Board of Trustees. He was 76 years old and was one the last ties to Peabody Normal, having attended the school, taught, served on several committees and boards, and known every president. He was the last professor of classical languages at Peabody, and continued to teach summer courses until 1945. Little maintained fifty years of connection with Peabody.
Mrs. Little died October 10, 1938, soon after Little moved in with his daughter, son-in-law, and grandson. Charles Little died on September 11, 1945 at 79 years of age. The funeral was held on Peabody’s campus in the Social Religious Building (now the Wyatt Center), and he is buried in the Peabody plot at Mt. Olivet Cemetery.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Charles E. Little Papers are comprised of .83 linear feet and contain 67 folders in two Hollinger boxes. The papers are divided into three series. The Academic Career series contains Little’s grade books as well as writings from his time as secretary and his time in Italy studying the Italian school system. The Correspondence series contains the largest of the materials are correspondences and copied correspondences. The copied correspondences are tied to Peabody, such as Peabody president Bruce Ryburn Payne or board of trustee members. In Series III The Peabody College materials include correspondences and as well as documents related to the college such as speeches, statistics, and library correspondences. Several folders are dedicated to the Affiliation Committee between Peabody and Vanderbilt which facilitated communication on dual enrollment of classes, sporting facilities, tuition fees, and plans for the joint library.
- Series I: Academic Career
  - Academic Career: Faculty Meeting Minutes, February 12, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Academic Career: Grade Book, Eatonton Academy, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Academic Career: Grade Book, University of Nashville, 1891-1893 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Academic Career: Grade Book, University of Nashville/Peabody, 1895-1896 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Academic Career: Grade Book, University of Nashville/Peabody, 1896-1897 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Academic Career: Grade Book, University of Nashville/Peabody, 1902-1903 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Academic Career: Grade Book, University of Nashville/Peabody, 1903-1906 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Academic Career: Visits to Italian Schools, October-December, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Correspondence: Bowman, Stuart H., 1924 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Payne, Bruce R, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Smith, Bolton, 1912-1920 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Smith, Bolton, 1921-1931 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Weaver, Rufus, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Weatherford, W.D. (YMCA), 1926 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Webb, Hanor A. – Webb School, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Weld, Harry P., 1911-1912 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Wharey, J.B., 1910-1912 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Wheelis, L.F. Maude, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: Whinery (Encyclopedia Britannica), 1912 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence: Wicker, Catherine, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence: Wilder, Albert, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence: Wilkins, R.A., 1912 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence: Wills (Postmaster), 1911-1913 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence: Wilson, E.B., 1913 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence: Woofter, T.B., 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence: Wuest, Robert, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing, 1910-1912 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing, 1913-1917 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence: Outgoing, 1919-1934 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence: Unidentified (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Copied Correspondence: Arnett, Trevor, 1929-1932 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Copied Correspondence: Dickinson, J.M., 1921-1926 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Copied Correspondence: Federal Emergency Administration of Public Works, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Copied Correspondence: Garrison, S.C. (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Copied Correspondence: Jones, B.B., 1933-1941 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Copied Correspondence: Long, L.J., 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Copied Correspondence: Payne, Bruce R., 1914-1926 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Copied Correspondence: Payne, Bruce R., 1914-1926 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Copied Correspondence: Payne, Bruce R., 1927-1935 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Copied Correspondence: Phelps, Shelton, 1927-1931 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Copied Correspondence: Roosevelt, Theodore, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Copied Correspondence: Root, Elihu, 1926, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Copied Correspondence: Sanders, J.T., 1941 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Copied Correspondence: Taft, William H, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Key to Correspondence Numbering System- Many of the materials have a numbering system written in red or blue added by a researcher at a later date. The researcher included this rough guide with the papers. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series III: Peabody College
  - Peabody College: Affiliation Committee, Correspondence, 1914-1917 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Peabody College: Affiliation Committee, Correspondence, 1920-1929 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Peabody College: Affiliation Committee, Correspondence, 1930-1933 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Peabody College: Affiliation Committee, Library Plan of Cooperation, 1929-1932 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Peabody College: Affiliation Committee, Unidentified (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Peabody College: Board of Trustees (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Peabody College: Cullum, Edward Neely-Thesis Draft, “George Peabody College for Teachers, 1914-1937” (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Peabody College: Dickinson Commencement Address, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Peabody College: Faculty By-Laws, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Peabody College: Faculty Questionnaire on Grades (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Peabody College: Hoover Speech Excerpt, New Deal and Higher Education (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Peabody College: Library School Correspondence, April 1929-October 1929 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Peabody College: List of Dissertations, 1914-1937 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Peabody College: Payne Speech (Recollections of Hanor A. Webb) (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Peabody College: Peabody Architecture and Landscape (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Peabody College: Peabody Educational Program (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Peabody College: Peabody Library Correspondence, 1930-1935 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Peabody College: Peabody Library Correspondence, 1936-1944 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Peabody College: Peabody Library- Didcoct, John J. Correspondence, 1935-1937 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Peabody College: Peabody Library- Didcoct, John J. Correspondence, 1938-1940 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Peabody College: Peabody Library- Didcoct, John J. Correspondence, 1941-1944 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Peabody College: Statistics (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Peabody College: Suggestions of Southern Association Regarding Peabody Administration (Box 2, Folder 31)